this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size we're
moving infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
one hundred dollar infrastructure credit
at doco / SC radio hello this is Kishore
Bhatia for software engineering radio
today's episode is about the landscape
of practicing and testing for
development skills coding interviews and
automated skills assessment in developer
hiding with Vivek Ravi Shankar Vivek is
the founder and CEO of hacker ranked a
platform that's helping programmers
globally to learn in practice coding we
really calls previously a part of the
Kindle team at Amazon India with bacon
QB ed hacker ranked as the first company
to be accepted by Y Combinator from
India welcome to software engineering
radio Vivek thank you - or happy to be
here being hacker ranked would have you
seen in the need for coding interviews
evolving that led you to hacker rank you
know obviously every company's becoming
a software company and every company is
hiring a lot of developers because that
is that is becoming the core for your
company but the interviewing technique
were still very old school like people
still ask candidates the right code on
their whiteboard or just read out code
on your phone or maybe they can send
over take home challenge where they have
to attach a zip file and you have to
download and go ahead and run it so the
methods that were used were very archaic
and that's one of the reasons what did
us to building a product that can help
streamline the entire process and also
make it focused on the skills versus
their pedigree
or resume or other kind of or other kind
of data points that can skew your your
hiring process and how if the interview
process has evolved so far where is the
standard now I think a lot of companies
have started to stop doing white board
coding they actually have resorted more
into having more of a pair programming
interface where you can see the other
person code so things have they've
started to use more technology tools
like hack Arang
but the interview process so it is
definitely gotten closer to real-world
of what you would do in a coding and
evaluating skills on that versus using
those old techniques so when it comes to
the platforms that are helping coding
interviews is that right now more of a
collaborative platform to do an online
digital native whiteboard or are there
more new answers to such platforms yeah
I think I I think the goal of every
company are probably most companies I
should say is to try and see if you can
mimic a real-world experience for a
candidate because that's the best way
for you to figure out how effective this
person is and I think all the products
and hacker and being sort of leading it
from from the front we've evolved into a
way where it's it's it's closer to a
real-world experience and you can almost
simulate what you would do when you come
out to work in an interview process so
it wouldn't be just a translation of hey
what you would do in physical rooms and
we'll just move it to you know move it
and build an app over it like for
example you know people aren't building
an app for a whiteboard where you can
actually write code on an iPad but
people have evolved into what would be
what would you do in a real-world
setting and can you build a software
product based on that so that's that's
how things have come along and if we
take an example of you know a coding
interview that is going on for you know
a company that is doing it face to face
you know versus through a hacker rank or
up similar platform how would you
differentiate that as to the way that
digital native platforms have started
helping I think the traditional nav
process they have a lot of bias
associated with it the traditional
interview process has biased right from
the start of the process of where you
look at
somebody's resume and you immediately
get an image of the person based on the
name location school GPA pedigree places
that you worked before you get it you
get a mental picture of how this person
is and then you enter it you enter the
interview with the bias then the other
parts of the interview is also usually
interviews are pretty high-pressure
environment where as a candidate you
want to get a job offer and you have you
have this feeling that you need to prove
how strong you are within 45 minutes and
that's not that's not usually how your
real-world job goes so I think the
traditional set of interviews is has a
lot of inherent biases that that makes
that makes it hard to identify this
person as a fit or not what if you're
trying to build a hacker rank is too it
is how can we give a skill based way of
evaluating candidates in their own work
environment so when you give a take home
challenge and you give give it for like
okay here's the take home challenge and
it's open for a day it's not gonna take
you a day but it's only gonna take you a
few hours but we're gonna give you a day
for you to go ahead and solve this
challenge in your own environment and
then once we do this you know after you
solve the challenge will bring will
continue discussing this challenge when
you come on set in an interview so that
you don't have any card drawn kind of
questions but you're continuing the
interview process that's a way more
smoother better experience for the
candidate as well as helps the companies
figure out is this person the right fit
or not so that's huge change in the way
technical interviews are being done
right now I see your point so you know
in order to like and we'll definitely
jump into you know different aspects of
you know you mentioned something about
bias you mentioned something about you
know the the new technology skills that
we are evaluating for and the way it can
help you you know do that remote first
and then bring the candidate on-site I'm
also interested in learning more about
the foundational skills that you know
that the platforms you know evolve and
and help assess and into what depth are
we assessing this but you know taking
this from a recruiter and a hiring
managers perspective where does this fit
in today in order for you to build a
sourcing recruiting and hiring pipeline
can you describe how that works today
so traditionally it would be like a
recruiter who would call a candidate
and it would probably ask a set of
questions as a pre-screening way to go
ahead and do it and then if you clear
then you would continue the interview
process where the hiring manager would
have a pair programming session or a
phone interview
what has changed now is the start is is
more of a coding challenge where as a
developer you can showcase your skills
and based on of course the recruiter
calls the cept context so that give more
information about a company but they
don't do a lot of technical screens now
it's done by the code challenge and then
the hiring manager looks at the report
figures out what are the strengths and
weaknesses of this candidate and now you
can continue the interview process based
on that as that's that's a big shift
from what it used to be in and what's
happening right now
and in terms of the you know the users
of the platform is this always on the
recruitment side of it for employers or
is there a lot that the developers who
are learning to code or developers who
are honing in on you know a particular
scale or increasing their depth or
breadth of a particular area are also
learning on the platform you know we do
have like a community side angle to it I
don't know if that's what is is that
what you're referring to yeah like what
is the you know what is the engagement
of from a developer standpoint yep yeah
so there are there are different things
one is as a developer you want to
continue to practice before practice
test like hone your skills and get it
better so that's one thing that we have
found to be you know our community to be
pretty effective where you as a as a
candidate can sign up it's free for
developers at the practice how to code
before you attempt the test so that that
is that is a very very powerful
mechanism or you can do it and a lot of
people actually do it for fun because
they can actually get on the leaderboard
and showcase how well they are doing so
that's there has been while and then of
course the other workflow for a
candidate or developer is to attempt a
challenge for a company and then get
connected to the company get an
interview and and an offer through the
company's specific code challenge
god yeah right and there's this connect
overall for a single developers journey
from the community you know practicing
on the platform and then actually
getting assessed through the platform
for employment yeah if you think about a
developer who's looking for a job a you
know you have to practice skills which
you can actually do it in the community
it'd be you would probably have this
sort of if you'd like to do company
specific skills you know we have
customized interview prep tips where you
can go ahead and practice and get better
at understanding what each company wants
then of course if you'd like to get a
job with a company you can go ahead and
take the company's specific challenge to
get connected to the company so it does
play a pretty important role across the
board for a developer to practice for
jobs for fun you know practice company
specific questions as well as continuing
to get connected to the company through
our platform
I see in order to go beyond the overview
of how these platforms are coming up and
you know what is the actual use case we
are addressing here for developers as
well as for recruiters and hiring
managers I also wanted to understand you
know some of the things you found in the
developer skills report you know and
there's there's many of them there's
there's some Stack Overflow
you know it's also assessments that are
being done by the likes of tart works
and where the you know the technology
frontier is is actually going I am
specifically looking at you know
statements around the future of work
right and is there something you know
beyond the fact that all jobs are
basically now getting automated and
there's more and more focused on
learning how to code what is the theme
behind you know all of that and then how
do we prepare for some of that you know
evolution to bring in the kind of jobs
that we are looking for the kind of
training that we are looking for so I
just wanted to like focus for the next
5-10 minutes around the theme about
learning to code do you have some
perspectives based on your experience
before and now in hacker back ya know
it's it's it's definitely interesting
question of what as a future
job profiles look like I do believe the
idea of learning to code won't just be
restricted to an engineering org but it
would be pervasive throughout different
also the company and by the way for what
it's worth like coding is really is
really writing a set of rules to
automate or to build something
in the language to go ahead and build
then the project build an app that makes
your life easier I didn't mean that
that's why you code and as much as you
know it's not viewed as traditional
coding when you do your Excel formulas
that is also code you're basically using
a language that was using language that
is familiar to Excel you are building
something that makes your life easier
and so coding is already present in a
lot of different organizations beyond
engineering now what it's starting to
happen is that there are so many
different languages that are coming up
and some of them have very easy learning
curves and they are way more powerful
than what a simple Excel can go ahead
and do now what that ends up doing is
then people start to get a better sense
of oh wow this is super powerful and I
can get an answer to what I've been
looking for within half the time if I'm
able to build if I may be to build this
which is going to increase my
productivity and that's how that's what
you see a shift that's happening and
once you see that shift happening in in
marketing in data science in sales and
all of the different orgs then you start
to see the concept or the idea of coding
being more pervasive throughout
companies organization and then being
restricted to engineering so that's what
I think would happen it's not going to
be that everyone in the world although
it would be good but I don't think
everyone in the world has to absolutely
know the code otherwise there are no
jobs but what's gonna happen is every
organization in the future we'll have a
big encoding component to it way bigger
than what it is right now gotcha so like
software is eating the world and every
company is that company you know those
are the things that we are we're seeing
happening already as part of the shift
that we were seeing in business are
there any proofs on how the you know
like examples on how the you know
different domains within a company every
company every business has certain you
know certain org units and certain must
have operations that you were seeing
already being either automated or
software driven yeah well software is
eating the world is slightly is a
related one
but it's a tangential concept or
whatever I describes Opera eating the
world is more is saying that hey any
industries core will be technology and
they have to build an engineering park
but within that there's one more layer
what what I'm saying is every org within
the company will also be driven or will
have a much bigger engineering coding
component than what it is right now and
for an example if you'd like to take an
example I think earlier people used to
do either manual or a gut feel way of
figuring out if a lead is going to
convert into a real opportunity in
marketing or in sales like hey you know
is this prospect are they going to buy
our data right prospect and either it
used to be a gut feel or some some sort
of custom formula that you use right now
there are software's that using your
past data can analyze a particular
company on so many different parameters
like the size of the company inclination
to buy is it similar to the previous
companies like you know the quality of
the lead the quality of the contractors
just like hundreds of different
parameters that can help you process pay
off these ten you should go after these
three because they have a higher
probability to close and that is
basically a software or data science be
working behind that behind the scenes
now what what you can see is now there's
there's not gonna be a one there's not
gonna be any software that is as good as
writing something custom for your
company it's probably gonna take you 50%
60% all the way but you still have to do
some work on your own because there's so
many things that are custom for the
company and that's where you know a data
science organization it's not just gonna
be restricted to predicting whether this
user is going to be retain in your app
or not but the data sense organization
is going to also predict whether this
lee is going to convert into a
successful customer or not so then you
start to see that also moving across
different organizations the companies
that's an example of what used to happen
before based on just gut feel but now
it's data science and the do science
organization is actually in responsible
or influences the decision thanks for
that example I think that's that sets a
tone for also the next deep tie which is
really around
what is really leading to this this
whole coding interview scale aspect so
why is it that we are not able to
fulfill those software roles in the tech
engineering roles by the conventional
methods of you know having resumes and
and you know screaming resumes manually
and also looking at how we face folks in
a company environment we actually run
through very traditional ways of of
interviews and assessments multiple
rounds over like sometimes even panels
and different pour members like
assessing different attributes so I
wanted to like really go into the scale
aspect of this do you think that the
platform is also a need now more than
ever just because we are were just
hiring so many so many developers so
many engineering candidates across you
know different nurseries that it could
just become a way to scale that
digitally yeah I think I think it's more
it's yeah there are probably combination
there's probably a combination of a lot
of different factors one is the fact
that you know people if you look at
every every any technology people always
want to continue to improve technology
to increase your productivity and that
is that is anything as small as a
plug-in in your browser to the other end
of the spectrum which is automating
driving of cars like basically a
self-driving car so that you don't have
to drive so there is it's it's it's a
consistent it's gonna be a consistent
evolution or innovation of how
technology can make people more
productive so that's definitely one
dimension and clearly people have found
or be found or a lot of developers also
figure that interviews are broken and
it's not it's not giving the right
signal so that is definitely one of them
the other factors are similar to what
you mentioned because now the volume of
developers that companies want to hire
it's also going is also increasing and
and also they have to compete with every
other company so previously maybe 20
years back the sample set of number of
companies that were hiding lots and lots
of developers were a handful and now
there are like thousands and and that
becomes a very very hard challenge to do
to overcome and that's also one of the
one
why products like hacker rank and others
but based based on skill based hiring
have started to pick up and grow quickly
gotcha you know you mentioned something
about increasing productivity who are
the the end users our audience here to
kind of help increase this kind of
productivity on the code assessment code
skills within the platform what are we
trying to scale and who are the audience
or the end users that are you know
looking for you know increasing their
productivity in terms of maybe even
assessing different different coding
interviews yeah let's say it's the if
the recruiting and engineering arcs or
kind of go hand in hand and they
responsible for making sure that they
can build a very strong engineering team
and also retain them continue to build
them and retain them for a long time
right so it's a it's a combination of
the recruiting and the engineering or
that we help to increase their
productivity this then begs the question
around the difference between the
generating org that is that is also
looking for you know various attributes
beyond coding and the recruiters that
are looking for a match to more of a
specific skill set and the company's
requirement so how does that transition
from the recruiter looking for a
specific skill a specific job
description and maybe a specific set of
attributes to the hiring manager or the
engineering all you know looking for a
perfect fit within the within the
organization so I wanted like see the
journey if if I'm an engineer looking
for a job how do I begin with the coding
assessment journey yeah I think I think
that probably like two questions
everyone is the recruiter and hiring
manager in alignment and the other one
that he asked last was from a candidate
side perspective how do you get started
with applying right so the first
question of recruiting and hiring
manager no alignment yes it is it's
definitely can get a lot better because
I think a lot of times things get lost
in translation
what a hiring manager oftentimes want is
a very very strong problem solver
preferably in a language or staff that
they're working on or not you know
that's that's just your preference but
oftentimes it could get translated into
oh we need rails developers and we go
out and source for for rails developers
in the community so one of the things
that we have been trying to work on
at hacker rank is how to how to get the
alignment between the recruiter and the
engineering based on agreeing on a set
of skills and actually putting a very
formal way of how we will evaluate the
skills which is essentially comes down
to the coding child that's one of the
reasons why we it's almost like a side
effect but a really good side effect
that we have seen with a lot of
customers where we have seen recruiters
actually come to us and say hey this is
improved our recruiting and hiring
manager relationship and alignment
because now we're absolutely aligned on
what is required for us to pass on to
the next round so that's the first part
of your question so it's a vertical
question was more on candidates applying
for a job yeah so the candidates that
are looking at jobs specifically in an
engineering org how do they begin their
journey on through the platform you know
using say a recruiter view and then an
engineering you know hiring manager
review I think it high-level a developer
who's looking for a job should probably
be very clear on you know the criteria
or certain things that they're looking
for a job there are hundreds of
parameters from compensation and wooden
compensation like how much devalue cash
how much do you value a query size of
company impact in that pretty lateen
that you're working on the people that
are gonna work on location this the fact
that the company's working on that is
there are like hundreds of different
parameters and I would recommend every
developer any developer who's looking to
change the job to make sure that you
have three must-haves and the rest of
them are all nice to have what are the
three absolute must-haves that you won't
compromise and for some people it might
be location and for some people it might
be the stock that you're working on for
some people it might be the size of the
company it cannot be more than hundred
people so one of the three must-haves
and then help identify and now you can
go ahead for your next step on
identifying companies that fall into
that structure then you can go ahead and
apply and the way we help ease out the
application process is going through a
code challenge versus complying through
a job board or or already a carriers
page which usually results in some kind
of a black hole because you really don't
know if somebody's gonna contact you is
this is this even that I fit it's
usually result in the black hole so that
is one of the one of the things that
we're
already started work on many would see
more of that coming along where we want
to ease the application process through
to be based on skills and almost
directly get in front of the hiring
managers our on-site interviews versus
going through phone interviews phone
interview to phone interview three and
then coming to one side it just becomes
a elongated long process well that's a
very insightful point you just made so
if I am a you know and I would like you
know look at this from both perspectives
developer applying as well as an
employer looking for the best talent if
I am a company you know looking for
something best talent how do I actually
create challenges exciting enough I
don't know maybe game theory maybe you
know some kind of an incentive to
attract the best talent and maybe even
you know somehow growth Hackett to to
ensure that I actually get enough
engagement from these best talent you
know communities which would then even
feel like okay I would actually go and
solve that challenge and apply yeah
there's no one perfect answer to that
there are probably lots of a lot of
different ways that he can go ahead and
do it but one of the things I would say
is to make sure that that you can invest
in any of your advertising campaigns or
challenges or anything to tell
developers on the kind of problems that
you're working on I think that is super
critical and a lot of companies actually
don't do that because any developer
wants to know how it is to work once I
come on border what are the problems
that you're tackling and usually these
problems are written inside a job
description with a couple of sentences
but you know it's hard to exactly
understand the intensity or the depth of
the problem unless you go ahead and try
it out or unless you have a sample where
you can go ahead and practice so that's
that's one big driver or a major factor
of what companies can do to attract
developers saying hey here is an example
challenge that we're solving to attract
people who would be interested to take
on the challenge great and and when a
developer does that you're saying that
it basically directly gets that
developer in front of the hiring manager
skipping the whole line of you know
screening resumes you know for
interviews how has that been enabled by
the platform's you know today is it just
sure I post my challenge there and a
bunch of folks would put solve those
challenges
and you just call them in like how how
does that process work yeah I wouldn't
say that we're doing it right now that
could be like a good state if you aim
for what I what I really meant was in
that aspect was there are just a lot of
Hoops to go through right now and even a
skill-based challenge you could almost
imagine okay you have these skills and a
recruiter just ensures they can call
them up and ensure hey are you really
interested in the company and they can
check about talk to them about the
culture fit is it are they a good fit to
them and can essentially fast-track the
process right without without looking
through okay let me scare your phone
screen one phones me into and on sites
and others that's something that we are
pushing towards and a lot of our
customers have actually started doing
this and even skipping their our company
soaps completely eliminated phone
interviews in this case because they
have they get very high signal from the
candidates score that's the direction in
which I believe will be less biased
based on skills there's also great
experience for the recruiting hiring
managers as well as the candidates
digitalocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy manage and scale
applications of any size
removing infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
one hundred dollar infrastructure credit
at doco /sc radio I think in this couple
of questions I really want to focus on
the the type of skills that we can
evaluate through this cool screening
process and the ones that are more media
abstract and in meant for on sites or
face to face can you go into a into that
depth a little bit yeah I think if you
take a typical troll there's probably a
bunch of different technical skills and
then the other part is the culture site
or the core value fit that that needs to
be taken care so the technical skills
you know we try to cover as much as
possible you know some of the things
that we're working on if you're not yet
covered is your architecture skills how
do you design s3 for example or how do
you how do you design a system that can
store a billion photographs and retrieve
it very quickly I mean there are there
are different questions on those lines
where you're not expected to really code
but you're expected to share the
architecture diagram and it's very hard
to evaluate the quality of the of that
architecture diagram in an automated way
so we try to do a lot of the technical
interviews that people do manually in a
very automated way except for a few
things like the system design in
architecture and others and then there's
a whole set of core value or the culture
site which is super important super
critical that usually there is a there
is a thread that runs throughout the
interview which is everybody assesses
the candidate for that but there's also
you've seen it a lot of companies is
specific dedicated round that's done on
the core value or the culture fit that I
there are people who are actually
working on trying to get more signals in
a kind of a gamified way it has seen
success but I'm not sure how how well
that can scale because
you do require that human touch I
believe on figuring out hey can you and
I work together and that's something
that we have not explored much and I
don't have any more ideas then okay
maybe in the future something might
happen to automate that so that's that's
one of the one of the places where we
have not explored much and that's an
example of one thing that we have not
automated and in terms of just the
coding interviews and the skills
specific to say a language or an
ecosystem are these interviews to some
extent even stressing out on the the
knowledge of a framework like in say
Java
you're talking about spring boot or
we're looking at how one would go about
doing dependency injection or write you
know a simple structured set of classes
and I can actually now just on
readability and some other aspects so
like how far does the the view automate
things on a depth and a treads
perspective yeah I think we do it we do
it really deep you can do it right from
a simple here is a code single file code
go ahead and debug do all the way to
build an app on react or on node so you
we have we can cover a pretty wide
spectrum of what you can do and also
from from a scoring evaluation
perspective we check for correctness we
check for optimality which is the code
complexity we'll also check for like
code quality we run a cold polity tool
to to see if there are basic things like
unused variables function names are they
descriptive or not so we do we do a
pretty in-depth analysis of course as
always think that that's gonna be hard
to automate like it's a code elegant how
well it how beautiful it is in terms of
the comments to the functions and there
are sort of things that just cannot be
automated but we try to go to a pretty
large extent that can give you a lot of
signal right do you also test for
something like okay you were given this
this challenge and you have to solve
this in say JavaScript or maybe C or go
but you have to make sure that you say
pass these many tests in order to I call
it as code complete yeah yeah absolutely
we actually run every code against a set
of test cases which in each of them
assess a particular skill for the
candidate gotcha gotcha and how much of
this is transparent like is this is this
real
and it's already happening for the
candidate to start looking at the
results that you know he or she is
driving towards the amount of code that
you know you've written yeah everything
suspended a candidate can actually see
what's what's going on can go ahead and
update and iterate on that further they
can see what what the hiring manager is
saying so yes they can they can see
everything I think you mentioned
something about architecture and some
other transitions that might be much
more of a fit that you can test over say
a face-to-face interview on-site you
know in terms of the the switches
between you know different languages and
sometimes you know the the overall
experience is that all on-site or there
is some aspect here that the platform
can actually go and test
I think the stronger and better we get
in terms of assessing all of these
skills the fewer number of on-site
interviews you would have or the on-site
interview I'd see the texture of the
on-site interviews would change more
towards can you and I work together well
where it says do you have these skills I
see right and like you know going back
to our previous conversation about you
know how these platforms benefit overall
reduced bias can you deep Taiwan some
examples here yeah one of the example
stories that I tell tell often is VMware
has been a great customer of ours and
here was this candidate whose resume was
was literally a dishwasher in Spain
which would have likely you know you've
likely not continued an interview
process after looking at a resume but
then he had the opportunity to attempt
to be a more challenge cleared the
challenge got an offer in VMware and has
been promoted twice in two years which
is one of the fastest paths to getting
promoted and that's a great story well
that's a great example that proves the
mission that you know you should we want
to match every developer to the right
job based on their skills and not
pedigree so that's an example of how we
have been able to help reduce bias and
when you when you assess so many
candidates at different levels and for
different you know opportunities and
companies is there anything else that is
also generated as maybe a bunch of
insight into which ways are the
skillsets basically moving
what is the number of frameworks that
are mostly being used to say you know
develop on JavaScript or to do say you
know something on the back inside is
there any insight that you can just
bring on from a 20-18 report yeah I
think one of the interesting parts from
the 2018 report was how much people
wanted to learn the language go I think
it was one of the most popular languages
and things in the language that people
really wanted blood and the other
interesting insight to me there was
there was very interesting you know and
surprising in a good way
was how over 76% of developers actually
thought they were self-taught developers
even though they had a degree that they
were working at companies most of the
skills that they've learned to become a
very strong developer came from the fact
that they continued a lot of their own
so those two were very interesting
insights to me I do want to see you know
in terms of the you are all you know
coding languages and ecosystems
I was the platform also helping
continuous learning and evolving as the
technologies evolve you know are there
examples or investments that you've seen
that helps worked for employers and and
the you know developers on continuous
learning and evolving I think there are
two sides to it one is the continuous
learning and development within a
company you know what can we do to
encourage employees and others to
continue learn and develop the other
side is our community so I would say
anybody can come and sign up and
continue to learn on their own so we've
seen evidence or demand in both places
which is companies internally wanting
developers of their organizations to
continue to learn a new technology using
hacker and we've not explored that deep
but there's definitely a lot of demand
in that you know I wanted to now get
into the ways you look at the skills and
maybe even assess you know the overall
threat and depth you mentioned some some
of the examples around testing in code
optimal ways for you know assessing if
the candidate has the right level of
experience in maybe even coding with
that language or that ecosystem can you
give me some some examples of how that
process actually works like is that
mostly applying some level of learning
or is it more like you know comparisons
with how the best practices are applying
some design patterns on the results I
just
to understand from like a skills
assessment maybe picking up one language
of one ecosystem if he can go to that so
in a high level I think what people want
to assess a candidate on a particular
role let's say if it's a back-end
developer or a front-end developer or
something on those lines is you know do
you have strong problem-solving ability
do you have a knowledge of a framework
you would prefer if you had knowledge of
the framework that we are working on but
as long as you're proficient and at
least one language of framework that's
good do you have the right architecture
or system design skills to make that
scalable and finally are you a fit to
the company in terms of culture and core
values
so that's summarizes most of the hiring
process if I had to classify put them in
four buckets and so we try to do I would
say problem-solving the knowledge of
framework or a particular language we
can build a real-world app or debug an
app that's built on the particular
language or the framework and we also do
architecture and system design it's sort
of like a beta ish way we've not figured
yet on how to automate sort of scoring
how good is this architecture but we do
support for people to draw diagrams
architecture diagrams on our on our
product in terms of how we evaluate
there are so many different parameters
so one is doesn't give you the right
answer that's kind of the basic
fundamental thing is whatever you're
doing giving you the right answer the
second one is how fast does it run and
there are different code complexities of
earth n where's this n square with n log
n so we try to understand based on the
different test cases that the code runs
on what is the code complexity of this
particular code and then there's also
the code elegance of the code quality
aspect of it where we try to run sonar
or some code quality tool to help
understand could have things being
written better good things have been
refactored in a different way there
aren't used variables and things on
those lines so we try to have a very
in-depth analysis across each of these
different parameters for problem solving
or a real-world challenge and we're
working towards having something similar
for the system design as well that's
that's amazing when it comes to some of
the some of the ways you have like
applied that learning into building up
for what the employers are looking for
and then maybe enhancing some of the
ways to even high
how has that worked out for the employer
side of it is it that when you like say
assessing hundred candidates and I'm
just picking an example Sophie did I
correct me if you're picking up like
hundred candidates for a single position
and that leads into ten on sites how
does that ratio today work out in a in
an automated screening process yeah no
absolutely I think I think people have
been able to reduce the time to hire by
50 to 70 percent using hacker rank and
that's a huge gain especially when
you're hiring hundreds of developers
even if you're hiring like even 10 to 50
developers that's still reducing your
time to hire by half is can just give
you massive amounts of product ability
and the in terms of so that's that's one
quantitative number but there are also
other things that are more qualitative
that's hard to measure one is the fact
that you have a consistency in the bar
of the hiding bar in your company the
second one is the fact that as a
recruiter now you can open up your open
up the net to a much broader set of
candidates versus restricting them based
on the school and the GP and the
companies that they work before so there
are a lot of other qualitative
advantages as well that can give you
that product like hacker I can give
apart from the fact that it reduces the
time to hire by half and when it comes
to sourcing are you thinking through how
a particular level of filter is applied
right away the end is it just a job
description or because the platform
itself is global and and web-based you
know now anyone can actually go ahead
and like you know apply or solve that
challenge and come in through so we kind
of touched upon this in the question
about the bias right but in in case of
trying to filter through you know the
say collocation for example is a big
criteria or you know or maybe the number
of years of experience is a big criteria
even though you could be a very good
coder on a certain aspect
have you seen anomalies with a web
platform that could basically now give
you something that you didn't know in in
creating a Job Description definitely I
think I think even generally a job
description in itself is probably really
biased and there are actually companies
I think there's a company called textio
that parses a job description and
tells you ideas that you can actually go
in and improve to attract a more diverse
set of candidates so job description in
itself is is a very can the biased way
to attract people you're likely going to
see the people usually copy based job
descriptions from other companies for a
particular role and years of experience
is usually viewed as a proxy towards
your mastery in that particular field I
don't I don't believe in job
descriptions a lot and that's why we try
to help companies come up with a skilled
rubric for what they what they would
like to assess for each of these
different roles come up with that build
an assessment based on that and then
have hire people based on skills versus
relying on job descriptions can you get
into a little bit of details as to how
that skill matrix maybe works in terms
of applying say some score screening
into it and then you know maybe maybe a
little bit more like how is it
increasing diversity yeah so if it's in
a job description you're probably going
to say hey I need five years of
experience when you're trying to build
an assessment you would say I need this
person to be able to solve this problem
and be able to get to this level and and
that's that's the minimum bar so you
make it way more quantifiable and you
know what if this person gets into level
three of this challenge then we maybe we
should consider this person for a senior
or not a junior role or not a mid-level
role so you get into more quantifiable
way of defining skills and also it
removes the bias of years of experience
and you're actually open to hiring
somebody with two years of experience at
a senior level because they've just been
really good and they're able to solve
are they able to clear through the
hurdles that you've kept on level 2
level 3 for each of these challenges
they're able to solve something that
only a senior developer would be able to
code but they only have three years of
experience so that's a big difference of
what we've been able to see from
companies and on that note then for
developers like how does one
continuously adapt to newer ways of
getting hired and this is not just about
rescaling or learning you know
continuously but if the way is to hire
itself are changing and no more
dependent on just experience or you know
or a job description how can one for
cuz say as you mentioned something
related to problem solving or proving
that you know you can actually take this
challenge and after that you know
there's a there's a higher guarantee
that you can get in yeah I know that's a
great question and that's actually one
over long-term vision of the company as
well which is can we identify the DNA of
all of the different job roles and what
they want in terms of skills and can be
mapped that or help companies or help
developers sorry to understand hey here
is your skill level and if you'd like to
get it back in developer job at this
particular company here are these areas
that you need to get better or here are
the skills that you need to improve to
get there so that's some that's that's
our that's essentially our mission of
matching a video available to the job
based on your skills for the companies
you know that are basically looking at
scaling their hiring and then
continuously evolving landscape of the
ways to hire and the places where they
can find the best talent with you know
challenges such as these what are you
seeing as as evolution to to where this
is and in the challenges that the
companies still face I don't think
there's a silver bullet where we would
solve like okay we actually solve hiring
we can just continue to make strides on
getting better at identifying and
matching the right people to the jobs
but I don't think that's going to be a
silver bullet so the challenges will
still continue remain because there's
healthy competition and that there's
only going to get more intense because
you're gonna see more and more companies
in more and more industries won a table
software so this is so the challenge of
competition the challenge of the fact
that hey developers have way more
options now and it's going to continue
to increase for a very long time so
you're gonna see all of that come
through which is never going to stop but
our goal and mission at hydronic is
continue to improve the process of
helping a developer get connected or
match to the right job based on your
skill I think from like the coding
skills perspective we we kind of
understand the landscape when it comes
to the you know the employer is there is
there more of an involvement indirectly
or directly from like a pizzelle
operations or in HR perspective that
they can use these tools yeah I mean the
that you mean the recruiting department
like the recruiting department is
definitely one one you know upfront you
know organizational unit that is looking
for candidates but what about once the
candidate is in like you know is there a
is there a usage where you know some of
the some of the recruiting history as
well as you know new performance you
know in retaining candidates as well as
in growing in your employees you know
developer specifically are their usages
that are being driven by continuous like
code assessments or maybe continuous
certifications yeah I think that's the
the internal Learning and Development
that that we're seeing a lot of demand
for so there's definitely a lot of
opportunity there I mean and companies
like Coursera Udacity and others have
already started to work towards that
like their Enterprise Solution is
basically one of what you're describing
a lot of companies are also started
using hacker rank for that purpose but
that's a completely new dimension that
we need to undertake if you want to
double down in that space we've not yet
double down on that
although I can confirm that there's a
huge demand for that kind of solution
and like if you flip this now towards
the way we are actually training our
developers be it schooling you know
academic institutions and also post
educational trainings how is this
influencing or even helping that is
there a way we can start taking some
signals I see the developer report kind
of guiding us through the evolution of
different languages and you know where
is the most demand you know developers
basically looking at popular tech giants
and they you know taking some some hints
around
where should I basically invest my
career learnings to the the question is
now that is all that survey result is is
pretty much popular and everybody has
access to that information is there a
way that including hacker rank like
there is you know some level of
influence on on how the student
community you know the education
community is actually learning from that
we try our best and like I mentioned
before I mean our vision or aim is to
help developers understand here's the
DNA of all of these different job roles
and here's where you stand and help them
build a path towards getting those
skills so that's we are making progress
on that I don't think we've shipped a
lot of the
DNA's of job roles and the paths towards
that in production but that's something
that you're consistently working on
great and we're always almost coming
towards the wrap this I'd like to ask
you personally how do you keep pace with
no continuous learning and evolution in
tech my to do is learning an evolution
intact is more from talking to customers
and developers in that because my job
function and my job role has
continuously changed a lot and now I'm
more into focusing on how we can make
sure that we can recruit a great team
align the team towards a common mission
and goal so it's my job function and
roles have changed so I keep in touch
basically by with our developer
community and with our customers and
what they're looking for what are the
new skills and how things can continue
to evolve yeah do you have any
particular references for your own
reading or blogs or maybe podcasts that
you listen to it is not nothing any
particular hacker news is definitely
very popular which I you know it's
almost like a daily ritual for me to
look through hacker news I think the
best way to really keep in touch with
the latest technology is to code and and
to really understand that I need to make
time I don't have that right now at this
point in time but that's to me the best
way and since I don't have the luxury of
doing that immediately I'm trying to
augment it by whatever you mentioned
whether it's podcasts or blogs are
talking to customers talking to
developers and understanding how things
work but the best way is to mister code
trade thought to end the podcast on
coding skills do you have a presence on
Twitter or LinkedIn where we can you
know our audience can follow you yeah I
am on Twitter I'm at our the rake one
Twitter
sure I'll mention that in the links
perfect thanks a lot for being with us
here on the podcast yeah absolutely
thank you so much for sure and I'm
looking forward to seeing his life
digitalocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy manage and scale
applications of any size
removing infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
one hundred dollar infrastructure credit
at doco /sc radio thanks for listening
to se Radio an educational program
brought to you by Triple E software
magazine for more about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website at SE - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio slack calm you can
also email us at team @ SC - radio net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening